Welcome back.
잘 돌아왔어요
So about ten minutes later, maybe 15 minutes later, the run has completed.
10분에서 15분 정도 지나자 마라톤이 끝났어요
And how do I know this?
어떻게 아냐고요?
A few ways.
몇 가지 있죠
One of them is that I just got an email from OpenAI, as you can see right here in my email, uh, to
오픈AI에서 이메일이 왔습니다 여기 보이듯이 제 튜닝에
tell me that my fine tuning job.
대해 알려 주네요
Blah blah blah has successfully completed and a new model, blah blah blah has been created.
어쩌고저쩌고가 성공적으로 완료됐고 새 모델, 어쩌고저쩌고가 생성됐어요
And you'll notice in the name of that model there is that word processor, because we specifically asked
모델의 이름에서 워드 프로세서가 보이시죠. 프로세서에 접미사를 포함하도록
for the suffix processor to be included.
특별히 요청했거든요.
Uh, just shows you how how it works.
어떻게 작동하는지 보여드릴게요
It's the name of a feat for fine tuning, and then the name of the GPT four mini variant that we've
미세한 조정의 위업 이름이죠 GPT 4 미니 버전의 이름이에요
been working with colon personal colon processor, and then a code at the end.
퍼스널 콜론 프로세서로 작업해 왔죠 그리고 마지막 코드예요
So that's my email.
이게 제 이메일 주소예요
Here is the JupyterLab.
여기가 유피터랩이에요
Uh, this was the thing we were running.
우리가 진행하던 거였어요
Um, and now we're looking at the final ten messages in the status, and you will see that it completed
현재 상태에 있는 마지막 메시지 10개를 보고 있는데요 단계가 완료된 걸 보실
step.
수 있죠
Um, the last five steps here then.
마지막 다섯 계단이에요
Fine tune model created.
파인 튠 모델이 완성됐어요
Evaluating model against our usage policies before enabling.
사용하기 전에 사용 정책에 대항해 모델을 평가하는 거죠
That was the thing I mentioned to you that it does.
제가 말씀드린 게 그거였어요
Um, and then usage policies complete and the job has been successfully completed.
그러면 사용 방침이 완성되고 작업이 성공적으로 완료되죠
And that is that I will now show you in weights and biases how this looks.
이제 무게와 편향으로 어떻게 보이는지 보여드릴게요
This is the final weights and biases chart.
이게 최종 무게와 편향도 도표예요
Um, you can see that the things that really matter are training loss and validation loss uh, that
여기서 정말 중요한 건 훈련과 검증 손실입니다 검증 손실은
you can see that the validation loss of course, is not or didn't happen nearly as regularly as the
정기적으로 계산된 훈련 손실만큼 발생하거나 일어나지
training loss was calculated.
않아요
Um, and as I say, because again, because we only did one epoch that all of the training data was
다시 말씀드리지만 저희는 한 시대를 개혁하면서 모든 훈련 데이터가 새로워졌어요
So the training loss, uh, is, is just as useful for us, um, or the validation loss because it's
훈련의 손실은 검증의 손실만큼이나 유용해요 항상 한 세트에서
always calculating it on the same set.
계산을 하니까요
It's particularly useful for, for trying to spot trends.
유행을 파악하는 데 특히 유용하죠
Um, and at first blush, looking at the validation loss, there doesn't appear to be much of a trend
언뜻 보면 검증 손실을 보면 별다른 추세가 없는 것 같아요
there, which again, is concerning.
그래서 걱정이죠
We can bring this up.
이 얘기를 꺼내죠
We can edit this panel and zoom in.
이 패널을 편집하고 확대할 수 있어요
We can change the y axis here.
여기서 y축을 바꿔도 되고요
And the minimum should be zero.
최소 0달러는 받아야죠
And let's make the maximum like three.
최대한 3개로 하죠
So we zoom all the way in.
줌 인을 하죠
And you can see that it doesn't particularly look like it's improving.
보시다시피 나아지는 것 같지 않아요
In fact um, you could if you wished, uh, be uh, almost argue that maybe it's increasing slightly.
사실, 이렇게 말할 수도 있어요. 조금씩 증가하고 있다고요.
Um, but uh, I'm not sure if that we can necessarily say that there is a smoothing function that's
하지만 스무딩 함수가 이 차트에 있는지
available in this chart that we can go with, and that is the smoothed version of it.
잘 모르겠네요 스무딩 함수 말이에요
Uh, and, uh, yes, I suppose it's, it's certainly not going up, but it appears that it made some
네, 확실히 올라가진 않지만 뭔가 개선된 것 같아요 그리고
improvements and then it just kind of stayed flat.
평평하게 유지됐죠
But it does look like there was some improvement up until the 300 point.
하지만 300점 이전에는 개선이 있었던 것 같아요
Um, so these are all things for you to look at and spend more time on yourself.
이런 것들을 보면서 시간을 더 들여 보세요
But at this point, it's time for us to now go and evaluate this model against our test data.
하지만 이제 테스트 데이터를 대상으로 이 모델을 평가할 때예요
So I will kick that off and then flip to a video when it completes.
이걸 차고 있다가 다 되면 비디오로 돌릴게요
So let's go back to the Jupyter Lab.
그럼 주피터 연구소로 돌아가죠
So this is our fine tuned model right here.
이게 저희가 만든 미세 튜닝 모델이에요
Um we can get the job ID and we can collect the fine tuned model.
get ID를 얻어서 미세 튜닝 모델을 수집할 수 있어요
Let me just quickly show you what that's going to be.
어떻게 되는지 간단히 보여드릴게요
If I, um, show you this, you can see when we look in here now that right here there's a new attribute
이걸 보여드리면 여길 보시면 바로 여기에 새 특성 미세 조정 모델이 있는 걸 보실 수 있습니다 이메일에
fine tuned model, and it contains that same name of the fine tuned model that was in the email as well.
있던 미세 조정 모델의 동일한 이름도 포함하고 있죠
So you could equally copy and paste it from the email, but we might as well just pluck it out with
이메일에서 복사, 붙여넣기를 할 수 있지만 코드를 이용해서 빼내는
some code.
게 낫겠죠
So here we do.
여기 있네요
Uh, so just to show you that that's done when I'm suggesting, obviously if I run this, it's got that
제가 제안할 때 완료됐다는 걸 보여드리기 위해 이걸 실행하면 같은 이름을
same name.
갖게 되죠
All right.
좋아요
So we're going to redo this messages for function again.
함수에 대한 메시지를 다시 할게요
Uh, this time, uh, I'm, uh, just using the one that doesn't reveal the answer.
이번에는 어, 답이 없는 것만 사용할게요
Obviously, we don't want to give it that information.
물론 그 정보를 주고 싶진 않아요
Uh, let's just convince ourselves that that is actually going to work.
그게 통할 거라고 스스로를 설득해 보죠
There you go.
여기요
So it gives the question.
그래서 질문이 생기죠
It does not reveal the price.
가격은 안 나와요
And the challenge for our model is going to be to finish this off.
모델에게 주어진 과제는 이 부분을 완성하는 거예요
You will remember from last time a utility function that we that we have that will pluck out the price
기억하실 거예요 지난번에 나온 유틸리티 함수요 돌아오는 것에서 가격을
from what comes back.
추려내는 거죠
Uh, and I remember last time I did this, the price is roughly 99.99 because blah blah, blah.
지난번에 이걸 했을 때 대략 99달러였어요 99는 어쩌고저쩌고죠
And if we run that of course get price function just strips out the price from there.
실행하면 get 가격 함수에서 가격을 벗기는 거죠
Uh, as I think you're familiar.
이미 알고 계시겠지만요
So then this is the function, the function that we will be about to test against.
이게 함수입니다 우리가 시험할 함수죠
GPT fine tuned response is OpenAI ChatGPT completions create you call it, just as you would call it,
GPT의 미세한 반응은 오픈AI 챗GPT 완성입니다 일반 GPT 4를 그렇게
for the normal GPT four.
부르는데요
Oh, same API.
같은 API네요
Exactly.
맞아요
There's only one difference, one tiny difference, minute difference.
아주 미세한 차이죠
That is this we don't pass in GPT four mini.
GPT 4 미니에서는 통과 못 하는 부분이죠
We pass in the name of our fine tuned model, this name right here, that is what we will send in to
미세 튜닝 모델의 이름을 전달합니다 바로 이 이름이죠 오픈AI에 보낼 거예요
And it will automatically it will know that that means that we want to use our fine tuned version.
자동으로 알 거예요 잘 조율된 버전을 사용하고 싶다는 의미라는 것을요
We take back the response, we get the price.
Get it, get it, get it, get it, get it, it, it! 응답을 취소하면 대가를 받는 거죠
So let's just print one example.
예제 하나를 프린트하죠
Let's print a test, uh, something from the first thing on our test set, which was that that thing
테스트 세트를 프린트해 보죠 테스트 세트에 처음 나온 건데 200달러나
that cost 200 and something that was, uh, caught me off guard.
주고 샀고 제가 예상치 못한 거였어요
And then we will call our GPT fine tuned for the first time.
그리고 GPT를 처음으로 파인 튜닝할 거예요
Let's see what one result looks like.
어떤 결과가 나왔는지 보죠
Okay, so that is the sorry, the the number we were looking at earlier was a training price.
네, 그게 죄송합니다 아까 보려던 액수는 훈련 비용이었어요
This is the price of the first test item.
첫 번째 테스트 제품 가격이에요
Uh, let's see what the first test item actually is.
첫 번째 테스트 아이템이 뭔지 보죠
So.
그래서요?
Let's have a look at it.
한번 보죠
It is an AC compressor repair kit for Ford, uh, body parts.
에어컨 압축기 수리 키트예요 포드 차체 부품용이죠
And, uh, so this is one that I had to do myself and, uh, yeah, obviously it's not done a very good
이건 제가 직접 해야 했던 작업인데 첫 번째 데이터 포인트를 제대로 처리하지 못했지만
job of that first data point, but who cares about one data point?
데이터 포인트 하나쯤이야 무슨 상관이죠?
What matters is doing it across the lot, at least the 250 that we've been using consistently for all
중요한 건 공장 전체에 걸쳐 하는 겁니다 적어도 모든 테스트에 일관적으로 사용했던 250g을
of our testing.
통해서요
So without further ado, let's run it off it goes.
그럼 지체 없이 실행해 보죠
So the first couple of results look a bit red, and then it looks a bit better and gets green, but
처음 몇 결과는 약간 빨간색이었다가 좀 더 좋아 보였다가 초록색으로 변했다가 다시 온통
then a whole bunch of red.
빨간색이었죠. 비트
So some mixed results here.
결과가 엇갈리네요
And at this point I'm not going to have you hanging for the 250 of them.
250년 동안 매달리게 할 순 없어요
I'm going to pause.
잠시 멈출게요
And then the next video we will reveal the outcome.
다음 영상에서는 결과를 알려드리죠
I will see you there.
거기서 봐요